Melvin Reji John

32 Brigantine Way, Duffryn, Newport, NP10 8EW

Mob: 07905399796, Email: 09mejohn@gmail.com, GitHub: Melvin24, Medium: @09mejohn

Personal Statement

Passionate and driven iOS developer with over five years of commercial experience. My determined and proactive approach resulted in success of numerous projects that shaped BBC as a corporation. I make it my goal to create software with the user in mind, creating applications with a useable and intuitive user interface experience. I also understand the importance of creating modular, documented and tested code. I am constantly striving to learn new technologies and look to ways to better myself in this rapidly changing industry. After many exciting projects I am currently seeking new challenges which will utilise my meticulous skills.

Key Skills

Programming: Swift (5+), Objective C (5+), Ruby (1), Java (4), Kotlin (< 1), JavaScript (3), HTML (4+), PHP (3+), CSS (4), Python (3), C (2), C++ (1), SQL (4+)

Development Software: Xcode (up to v11), Android Studio, Git, Jenkins, Test Flight, App Store Connect, Optimizely, HockeyApp

API/Clients: UIKit, WebKit, VAPOR, Combine, SwiftUI, CoreML, ARKit, SceneKit

Platforms: Mac OSX (5+), Windows (8+), UNIX/Linux (< 1)

Communication: Demonstrated oral and written communication skills during many projects, presentations and extracurricular activities.

Problem Solving: A systematic and determined approach to problem solving.

Teamwork: Played a valuable role as a team member and a team leader during several software projects at BBC, Sky and my degree. Worked efficiently with team members at workplace.

Employment History

Software Developer, BBC Digital, 2nd Floor, Dock House, Salford, M50 2LH

(March 2018 - Present)

- Part of a large team responsible for re-architecting the iPlayer code base.
- Oversaw and implemented multiple features that shaped iPlayer as it is today.
- Part of a cross platform team normally lead by Senior Software Engineers to drive programme discoverability.
- Proactive approach to development using TDD.
- Proposed and implemented the use of custom Xcode templates to team's work cycle which created the opportunity to speak at CodeMobile 2019.
- Presented advantages and disadvantages of Static and Dynamic libraries to the team to drive a framework driven initiative.
- Lead the implementation of obituary feature in iPlayer by escalating technical approach with my team.
- Introduced Image Caching in iPlayer where none existed.
- Drove the decision to implement SwiftLint in iPlayer.
- Worked on projects managed under Kanban, Scrum and Sprints with WIP limits.
- Implemented Slack Integration for Jenkins.

Software Developer, Sky UK, Sky 2, Leeds, West Yorkshire, LS10 1QG

(September 2015 - March 2018)

- Undertook a major role in developing a stable architecture for Sky's brand new Sky Sports iOS App in Swift using a custom VIPER Design Pattern.
- Worked with MVC, MVVM and VIPER iOS architecture patterns.
- Successfully completed a brand new DE Sky Sport iOS App with an unprecedented level of expectations in performance, stability and accuracy set by the product owners over in Munich.

- Oversaw feature expectation and implementation to produce the DE Sky Sport iOS App.
- Successfully collaborating with Sky Italia and releasing a brand new native iOS application in just 12 weeks.
- Was part of a small group to successfully release a project in Ruby Rails to emulate sky.com.
- Part of many successful hack days such as ARKit, Notification and User Login Flow.
- Prepared and presented multiple talks covering design patterns, Cocoapod dependencies and Core ML.
- Attended multiple iOS Conferences across UK to expand my iOS knowledge and skills.

Crew Member, McDonalds, 35 High St, Town Centre, Newport NP20 1GF

(July 2012 - August 2015)

- Worked well in teams under considerable pressure maintaining a high degree of accuracy.
- Established good customer relations.
- Ensured quality control.

Assistant, PC Planet, 440 Corporation Road, Newport, NP19 0GG

(2012 - 2012)

- Developed a strong passion to work in the hardware side of this business.
- Opportunity to deepen my knowledge on certain software used in computer repair also to grasp some of the day to day aspects of operating a technology concern.

Teacher, Kumon, 1A Lakeside Drive, Celtic Springs, Newport, NP10 8BB

(2008 - 2012)

- Teach and help students in Mathematics and English.
- Developed excellent communication skills by managing issues with student and parents.

Education

Cardiff School of Computer Science & Informatics

(2012 - 2015)

Course: BSC Software Engineering (Achieved: First

Class)

St Joseph's RC High School

(2010-2012)

4 A-Levels: Maths(A), Technology(B), Computing(B),

Physics(C)

Duffryn High School

(2006-2010)

9 GCSEs Including: Maths, Advanced ICT, Separate Science and English

Interest/Achievements

Reading Materials

The Verge, iOS Dev Weekly, Medium/IOS App Development, CocoaCasts

Conferences

iOSCon 2017, iOSDevUK 2017, Spoke at CodeMobile 2019, iOSDevUK 2019

Learning Guitar

Challenging as I have little natural musical ability.

Air Cadet: 2 hours of flying Group Tutor and Vigilant

Learned discipline, navigational skills, attendance, flying skills and shooting skills

Duke of Edinburgh Bronze Award

Selected to be the team leader for navigation and group organisation. Involved problem solving and developed a sense of responsibility.

References

References are available upon request.